OK, good morning. So today, we're going to
早上好  今天我们要
continue our exploration of multithreaded algorithms.
继续对多线程算法进行探索
Last time we talked about some aspects of scheduling,
上一节课 我们介绍了一些线程调度方面的内容
and a little bit about linguistics
还讲了一点术语
to describe a multithreaded competition.
来描述多线程竞争
And today, we're going to
今天 我们要
actually deal with some algorithms.
实际接触一些算法
So, we're going to start out with a really simple,
我们由一个非常简单的例子开始
actually, what's fun about this, actually,
实际上 有意思的是
is that everything I'm going to teach you today
今天要教给你们的全部内容
I could have taught you in week two,
在第二周讲也是可以的
OK, because basically it's just
因为它基本上
taking the divide and conquer hammer,
就是在用名为"分治法"的神器
and just smashing problem after problem with it.
来刷掉一个又一个问题
OK, and so, actually next week's lectures on caching,
而实际上 下星期关于缓存的课
also very similar.
也是差不多的
So, everybody should bone up on their master theorem
所以每个人都要钻研一下它的主定理
and substitution methods for occurrences, and so forth
以及代入实际问题的方法等等
because that's our going to be doing.
因为这就是我们将要做的
And of course, all the stuff will be on the final.
当然 所有这些内容期末都会考
So let's start with matrix multiplication.
我们先从矩阵相乘开始
And we'll do n by n.
以n×n矩阵为例
So, our problem is to do C equals A times B.
问题是计算C=A*B
And the way we'll do that
我们使用的方法
is using divide and conquer, as we saw before,
是正如之前所见的分治法
although we're not going to use Strassen's method.
不过 我们不打算使用Strassen演算法
OK, we'll just use the ordinary thing,
只使用普通的方法
and I'll leave Strassen's as an exercise.
Strassen演算法将留作练习
So, the idea is we're going to look at
我们的做法是
matrix multiplication in terms of an n by n matrix,
把n×n矩阵的乘法
in terms of n over 2 by n over 2 matrices.
看成是n/2×n/2的矩阵的乘法
So, I partition C into four blocks,
我将C划分成四个区
and likewise with A and B.
A和B也进行同样的分区
OK, and we multiply those out,
将这些乘出来
and that gives us the following.
会得出下列结果
Make sure I get all my indices right.
确保所有的下标都无误
OK, so it gives us the sum of these two n by n matrices.
得到这两个n×n矩阵的和
OK, so for example,
举个例子
if I multiply the first row by the first column,
用第一行乘以第一列
I'm putting the first term,
第一项是
A_11 times B_11 in this matrix, in the second one,
矩阵里的A_11乘以B_11 第二个是
A_12 times B_21 gets placed here.
A_12乘以B_21放在这里
So, when I sum them, and so forth,
依此类推 将它们加起来
for the other entries, and when I sum them,
其它项都这样操作 全部加起来
I'm going to get my result.
我就能得到结果
So, we can write that out as a,
所以 我们可以把这个写成
let's see, I'm not sure
看一下 我不确定
this is going to all fit on one board,
能不能在一个板面里写完
but we'll see we can do.
应该能够写完
OK, so we can write that out as a multithreaded program.
我们可以把它写成一个多线程程序
So this, we're going to assume that
我们将会看到
n is an exact power of two for simplicity.
为简单起见 n恰好是2的幂
Since we're going to have two matrices that we have to add
因为我们要对两个矩阵相加
we're going to basically put one of them in our output, C;
那我们先把其中一个存进输出矩阵C里
that'll be the first one,
也就是第一个矩阵
and we're going to use a temporary matrix, T,
然后还要用到一个临时矩阵T
which is also n by n.
大小也是n×n
OK, and the code looks something like this,
它的代码是这样的
OK, n equals one, and C of one gets A of 1-1
当n=1时 C[1,1]等于A[1,1]
times B of 1-1.
乘以B[1,1]
Otherwise, what we do then is we partition the matrices.
其它情况下 我们对矩阵进行划分
OK, so we partition them into the block.
将它们分成几块
So, how long does it take me to partition at matrix into blocks
划分矩阵需要花费多少时间？
if I'm clever at my programming?
如果我是合格的程序猿的话
Yeah? No time, or it actually does
哈？ 不花时间 或者它实际上
take a little bit of time. Yeah, order one,
花费极少的时间 是O(1)的时间
basically, OK, because all it is
没错 因为所有这些
is just index calculations.
都只是下标运算
You have to change what the index is.
你还要做改变下标的运算
You have to pass in when you're passing these
你现在传参是 C[1,1] A[1,1] 这些
in addition to A, B, and C for example,
而不仅仅是A B C
pass and arrange which would
所以传参和整理的操作
have essentially a constant overhead.
就会多了一定的开销
But it's basically order one time.
但基本上是O(1)的时间
Basically order one time,
大致是O(1)的时间
OK, to partition the matrices
这是划分矩阵的时间复杂度
because all we are doing is index calculations.
因为只是做下标运算
And all we have to do is just as we go through,
我们要做的就是 在这过程中
is just make sure we keep track of the indices,
要注意跟踪下标的变化
OK? Any questions about that?
明白吧？ 有什么问题吗？
People follow? OK, that's sort of standard programming.
跟得上吧？ 很好 这是个很标准的程序
So then, what I do is I spawn multiplication of,
然后 我们递归地衍生出乘法
woops, the sub-matrices, and spawn——
衍生相乘这些子矩阵
——and continue, C_2-1, it's A_2-1,
——继续 C_21 A_21……
B_1-1, n over two, and let's see, 2-2, yeah, it's 2-1.
B_11 n/2 然后是C_22 A_21……
OK, and continuing onto the next page.
跨过楚河汉界继续写
Let me just make sure I somehow get the indentation right.
我要确认下 保证段首的缩进一致
This is my level of indentation,
这是段首缩进线
and I'm continuing right along.
我这边接着缩进线写
And now what I do is put the results in T, and then
现在我把结果放在T里 然后
OK, so I've spawn off all these multiplications.
好的 我把那些衍生递归乘法都写全了
So that means when I spawn,
那意味着 当我做衍生时
I get to, after I spawn something
当我衍生出一条语句
I can go onto the next statement,
我就可以接着衍生下一条语句
and execute that even as this is executing.
并执行它 即使上一条仍在执行中
OK, so that's our notion of multithreaded programming.
这就是多线程编程的概念所在
I spawn off these eight things.
我这里衍生出8条语句
What do I do next? What's the next step in this code?
然后做什么？ 代码的下一步应该是什么？
Sync.
同步
Yeah. OK, I've got to wait for them to be done
没错 我必须等它们跑完
before I can use their results.
才能用到它们的结果
OK, so I put a sync in, say wait for all those things
所以这里进行一个同步 等待所有
I spawned off to be done, and then what?
衍生的结果完成 然后呢？
Yeah. That you have to add T and C.
对 需要让T和C相加
So let's do that with a subroutine call.
调用一个子程序
OK, and then we are done. We do a return at the end.
子程序运行结束后 返回一个值
OK, so let's write the code for add, because add,
写一下加法的代码 因为如果可以的话
we also would like to do in parallel if we can.
我们也用并行处理来做加法
And what we are doing here is doing C gets C plus T,
这里要做的是用C加T来赋值C
OK? So, we're going to add T into C.
把T加入到C里
So, we have some code here to do our base case,
要先给基础情形写一段代码
and partitioning because we're going to
然后再写划分的代码  因为我们打算
do it divide and conquer as before.
跟之前一样 也用分治法来做
And this one's actually a lot easier.
而这个 实际上简单很多
We just spawn, add a C_1-1,
我们只需要衍生 加上C_11
T_1-1, n over 2, C_1-2, T_1-2,
T_11  n/2  C_12  T_12
n over 2, C_2-1, T_2-1, n over 2,
n/2  C_21  T_21  n/2
C_2-2, 2-2-2, n over 2, and then sync,
C_22  T_22  n/2 然后是同步
and return the result. OK, so all we're doing here is
然后返回结果 我们这里所做的
just dividing it into four pieces, spawning them off.
只是将其分成四个区 然后衍生下去
That's it. OK, wait until they're all done,
就是这样 等它们全部完成时
then we return with the result.
再返回结果
OK, so any questions about how this code works?
关于这些代码的执行 还有没有问题？
So, remember that here,
那么 记住在这里
we're going to have a scheduler underneath
底层有一个调度程序
which is scheduling this onto our processors.
它负责调度这些运算给处理器
And we're going to have to worry about
而我们需要考虑的是
how well that scheduler is doing.
调度程序的性能如何
And, from last time,
在上一节课
we learned that there were two important measures,
我们学习了两种重要的度量方法
OK, that can be used essentially
它们就是用来
to predict the performance on any number of processors.
预测任意数目的处理器性能的
And what are those two measures?
是哪两个度量方法？
Yeah, T_1 and T infinity so that we had some names.
对了 T_1和T无穷 它们还有个名字
T_1 is the work,
T_1是功
good, and T infinity is critical path length, good.
很好 T无穷是关键路径长度
So, you have to work in the critical path length.
你要在关键路径长度上做功
If we know the work in the critical path length,
如果知道关键路径长度上做的功
we can do things like say
我们就可以知道
what the parallelism is of our program,
程序的并行度如何
and from that, understand how many processors
然后我们就能知道要用多少处理器
it makes sense to run this program on.
来运行这个程序才合适
OK, so let's do that analysis.
我们来做一下分析
OK, so let's let M_P of n
设Mp(n)做为
be the p processor execution time for our mult code,
p个处理器执行矩阵相乘代码的时间
and A_P of n be the same thing
同理 Ap(n)则为
for our matrix addition code.
执行矩阵相加代码的时间
So, the first thing we're going to analyze is work.
我们首先要分析的是功
And, what do we hope our answer to our work is?
我们理想的功的多少?
When we analyze work, what do we hope it's going to be?
当分析功的时候 我们希望它是多少？
Well, we hope it's going to be small.
我们当然希望它越小越好
I'll grant you that. What could we benchmark it against?
用我的头发担保 那要相对什么基准才算小？
Yeah, if we wrote just something
如果我们只是写一些
that didn't use and have any parallelism.
没有并行运算的代码
We'd like our parallel code when run on one processor
当只有一个处理器时 我们希望并行代码
to be just as fast as our serial code,
能够和串行代码一样快
the normal code that we would write to do this problem.
跟一般解决这个问题的代码一样快
That's generally the way that
一般来说
we would like these things to operate, OK?
我们希望做到这样 对吧？
So, what is that for matrix multiplication in the naive way?
那么 一般的矩阵运算是怎样的？
Yeah, it's n^3. Of course, we use Strassen's algorithm,
没错 是n^3 当然 使用施特拉森演算法
or one of the other, faster algorithms that beat n^3.
或者其它比n^3更快的算法
But, for this problem,
但对于这个问题
we are just going to focus on n^3.
我们只需要关注n^3
I'm going to let you do the Strassen as an exercise.
我打算让你们用施特拉森演算法进行练习
So, let's analyze the work.
分析一下功
OK, since we have a subroutine for add
因为我们有一个做加法的子程序
that we are using in the multiply code,
在乘法代码里面会用到
OK, we start by analyzing the add.
那么 我们就从加法开始分析
So, we have A_1 of n, OK, is,
A_1(n)等于
well, can somebody give me a recurrence here?
这一块 有谁能给出一个递归式吗？
What's the recurrence for understanding
有没有一条递归式能帮助我们
the running time of this code?
求出这些代码的运行时间
OK, this is basically week two.
这基本上是第二周的内容
This is lecture one actually.
实际上 第一节课就讲了
This is like lecture two or, at worst, lecture three.
这好像在第二节课 最多第三节课的内容
Well, A of 1 of n.
A_1(n)等于……
Plus order one, right.
加上θ(1) 是的
OK, that's right. So, we have four problems
没错 那么我们就有四个
of size n over 2 that we are solving.
大小为n/2的问题需要解决
OK, so to see this, you don't even have to know that
要理解这个 你甚至不需要知道
we are doing this in parallel,
我们是在搞并行运算
because the work is basically what would happen
因为这是在一台串行机器上执行的
if it executed on a serial machine.
它基本也是这样的
So, we have four problems of size n over 2
所以我们有四个大小为n/2的问题
plus order one is the total work.
再加上θ(1)即为工作总量
Any questions about how I got that recurrence?
对于这个递归式的推导 还有什么问题吗？
Is that pretty straightforward?
是不是非常直观？
If not, let me know.
有不懂直说喔亲
OK, and so, what's the solution to this recurrence?
那么这个递归式的解是什么？
Yeah, order n^2.
对了 θ(n^2)
How do we know that? Yeah, master method,
怎么知道的？没错 主方法
so n to the log base two of four, right, is n^2.
n的log4(以2为底)次幂 正好是n^2
Compare that with order one.
与θ(1)比较一下
This dramatically dominates.
这块毫无疑问占了主导地位
So this is the answer,
所以这就是答案
the n to the log base two of four, n^2.
n的log4(以2为底)次幂 即n^2
OK, everybody remember that?
大家都记得吧？
OK, so I want people to bone up
所以 大家都得抓紧学习了
because this is going to be recurrences,
因为这里都是递归
and divide and conquer and stuff
以及分治法等的内容
is going to be on the final,
期末肯定会考
OK, even though we haven't seen it in many moons.
即使我们已经好几个月没有接触过
OK, so that's good.
这个结果很好
That's the same as the serial.
它与串行运算是一样的
If I had to add two n by n matrices,
如果要相加两个n×n的矩阵
how long does it take me to do it? n^2 time.
需要花费多少时间？n^2的时间
OK, so the input is size n^2.
因为输入的矩阵大小为n^2
So, you're not going to beat the size of the input
那你不可能比这个大小还小
if you have to look at every piece of the input.
你必须关注输入的每个细节
OK, let's now do the work of the matrix multiplication.
现在继续分析矩阵相乘的功
So once again, we want to get a recurrence here.
那么再一次 我们要求这里的递归式
So, what's our recurrence here?
这里的递归式是什么？
Yeah? Not quite.
多少？不对
Eight, right, good.
8 是的 很好
OK, eight, M1, n over 2, plus,
8 M_1(n/2)加上
yeah, there's theta n^2 for the addition,
没错 另外还有θ(n^2)
and then there's extra theta one
还有额外的一个θ(1)
that we can absorb into theta n^2.
我们把它算进θ(n^2)里
Isn't asymptotics great? OK, it's just great.
上下不是惊人地相似吗？ 非常好
And so, what's the solution to that one?
那么这一个的解是多少？
Theta n^3, why is that?
θ(n^3) 为什么？
Man, we are exercising old muscles. Aren't we?
童鞋们 动动你们的生锈的脑袋吧
And they're just creaking. I can hear them.
我都听到它们氧化的声音了
Why is that?
为什么是这个？
Yeah, master method because we're looking at,
对 要用主方法 因为我们观察到…
what are we comparing?
我们参照的是什么？
Yeah, n to the log base two of eight, or n^3 versus n^2,
对 n的log²8次幂 即n^3相对于n^2
this one dominates order n^3.
这部分决定了是θ(n^3)
OK, so this is same as serial.
所以 这与串行结果是一样
This was the same as serial.
与串行计算的时间度相同
That's good. OK, we know
很好 我们知道
we have a program that on one processor,
我们的并行代码在单处理器上
will execute the same as our serial code
与它所基于的串行代码
on which it's based.
所执行的结果一样
Namely, we could have done this.
也就是说 我们可以做到这一点
If I had just got rid of all the spawns and syncs,
如果去掉所有的衍生和同步函数
that would have just been
这就是一个
a perfectly good piece of pseudocode
非常完美的伪代码
describing the runtime of the algorithm,
描述了算法的运行时间
describing the serial algorithm.
说错了 是描述了串行算法
And its run time ends up being exactly the same,
它们的运行时间也是一样的
not too surprising. OK?
喜闻乐见 对吧？
OK, so now we do the new stuff, critical path length.
现在看一下新的内容 关键路径长度
OK, so here we have A infinity of n.
这里有一个A_∞(n)
Ooh, OK, so we're going to add up
呼 我们这里要加上
the critical path of this code here.
这段代码的关键路径
Hmm, how do I figure out
嗯 我们要如何
the critical path on a piece of code like that?
计算代码段的关键路径？
So, it's going to expand into one of those DAG's.
好吧 要把它拓展到一个DAG图里
What's the DAG going to look like?
DAG图看起来是怎么样的？
How do I reason?
我的目的是什么？
So, it's actually easier not to think about the DAG,
实际上 如果不想DAG图的话还会更简单点
but to simply think about what's going on in the code.
只需要想想代码里做了些什么
Yeah?
你说？
Yeah, so it's basically,
没错 因为它基本上
since all four spawns are spawning off the same thing,
因为四个衍生操作所衍生出的结果都一样
and they're operating in parallel,
而且它们是并行运作的
I could just look at one.
那只需要看一个就好
Or in general, if I spawned off several things,
或者通常来说 如果衍生出好几个
I look at which everyone is going to
我就看在衍生出来的东西里
have the maximum critical path
拥有最大关键路径的
for the things that I've spawned off.
那一个衍生支
So, when we do work,
所以计算的时候
we're usually doing plus when I have multiple subroutines.
乘法子程序的功是相加的
When we do critical path, I'm doing max.
而求关键路径时 则是取最大值
It's going to be the max
我们求的是最大值
over the critical paths of the subroutines that I call.
所有子程序中的最大关键路径
OK, and here they are all equal.
在这里它们是相等的
So what's the recurrence that I get?
那这次又是什么递归式？
What's the recurrence I'm going to get out of this one?
这里我们能得到什么递归式？
Yeah, A infinity, n over 2, plus constant,
对  A_∞(n/2)再加上常量
OK, because this is
因为这就是
what the worst is of any of those four
那四个里任意一个的最坏情况
because they're all the same.
因为它们都是一样的
They're all a problem looking at
它们都是同一种情况
the critical path of something that's half the size,
都要取决于一半大小的关键路径
for a problem that's half the size.
取决于大小为一半的情况
OK, people with me? OK, so what's the solution to this?
大家都明白？那么它的解是多少？
Yeah, that's theta log n.
没错 θ(log n)
That's just, once again, master theorem, case two,
这只是再一次使用公式法 第二次了
because the solution to this
因为这个的解是
is n to the log base two of one,
n的log1(以2为底)次幂
which is n to the zero. So we have, on this side,
也就是n的0次幂 所以在这边是1
we have one, and here, we're comparing it with one.
在这里 拿它和1作对比
They're the same,
它们是一样的
so therefore we tack on that extra log n.
因此乘上一个额外的log n
OK, so tack on one log n.
额外的一个log n
OK, so case two of the master method.
主方法的第二种情况
Pretty good.
非常好
OK, so that's pretty good,
答案非常好
because the critical path is pretty short,
因为关键路径很短
log n compared to the work, n^2.
log n相对于功n^2
So, let's do, then,
那么 我们来...
this one which is a little bit more interesting,
这个会更有意思一点
but not much harder. How about this one?
但又不会更难  这个等于多少？
What's the recurrence going to be?
递归式是多少？
Critical path of the multiplication?
乘积的关键路径？
So once again, it's going to be
再一次 它会是
the maximum of everything we spawned off in parallel,
并行衍生出的子程序的最大值
which is, by symmetry, the same as one of them.
也就是 由对称可知 它们每一个都相同
So what do I get here? M infinity, n over 2,
所以这里得出什么？M_∞(n/2)
plus theta log n. Where'd the theta log n come from?
加上θ(log n) 这个θ(log n)是怎么来的？
Yeah, from the addition.
对 从相加函数里得来的
That's the critical path of the addition.
它是相加函数里的关键路径
Now, why isn't that the maximum of that with all the spawns?
怪了 为什么不是这些衍生操作的最大值？
You said that when you spawn things off,
你会说 当衍生出一些运算时
you're going to do them,
你都应该要先做...
yeah, you sync first.
没错 你要先进行同步
And, sync says you wait for all those to be done.
同步意味着 要等所有运算都完成
So, you're only taking the maximum,
所以 这一块你只能取最大值
and across syncs you're adding.
等同步完了 你要做的是相加
So, you add across syncs,
相加是在同步之后
and across things that you spawned off in parallel.
等所有并行的衍生处理完成 再相加
That's where you are doing the max.
这就是要取最大值的原因
OK, but if you have a sync,
一旦进行同步
it says that that's the end.
意味着并行的结束
You've got to wait for everything there to end.
你必须等待所有工作的完成
This isn't going on in parallel with it.
加法跟前面的运算不是并行的
This is going on after it.
而是在并行处理之后进行的
So, whatever the critical path is here,
所以无论这里的关键路径是什么
OK, if I have an infinite number of processors,
即使我有无限个处理器
I'd still have to wait up at this point,
在这里 我还是要等前面都做完
and that would therefore make it so that
因此这就使得
the remaining execution here was...
接下来的程序执行...
I would have to add whatever
无论加法这块的关键路径是多少
the critical path was to this one.
都要等到同步完成才开始
Is that clear to everybody?
大家都清楚了吗？
OK, so we get this recurrence.
所以得到这个递归
And, that has solution what?
最后的解是多少？
Yeah, theta log squared n. OK, once again,
对 θ(log²n) 再一次
by master method, case two,
由主方法的第二种情况
where this ends up being a constant versus log n,
因为这是常数 这是log n
those don't differ by a polynomial amount,
它们微分后不是多项式数
or equal to a log factor.
也不是一个log因子
What we do in that circumstance
在这种情况下我们要做的是
is tack on an extra log factor.
乘上一个额外的系数
OK, so as I say, good idea to review the master method.
正如我说的 复习下主方法是有帮助的
OK, that's great.
非常好
So now, let's take a look at the parallelism that we get.
现在看一下得到的并行度
We'll just do it right here for the multiplication.
我们在这边写乘法的并行度吧
OK, so parallelism is what for the multiplication?
对于乘法的并行度是多少？
What's the formula for parallelism?
并行度的公式是什么？
So, we have p bar is the notation we use for this problem.
对这个问题 我们用P帽来表示并行度
What's the parallelism going to be?
并行度是多少？
What's the ratio I take?
我取的比值是多少？
Yeah, it's M_1 of n divided by M infinity of n.
对 它是M_1(n)/M_∞(n)
OK, and that's equal to, that's n^3.
等于 上面是n^3
That's n^2, or log n^2, sorry, log squared n.
下面是n^2  啊 是log²n 不好意思
OK, so this is the parallelism.
这就是并行度
That says you could run up to this many processors
这表示 可以在这么多的处理器上运行
and expect to be getting linear speed up.
而且会得到线性的加速
If I ran with more processors than the parallelism,
如果运行的处理器数量多于并行度
I don't expect to be getting linear speed up anymore,
就不再期望能得到线性的加速了
OK, because I'll hit the bound what I expect to run in,
因为会到达极限 我们期望的是
is just time proportional to critical path length,
运行时间能跟关键路径长度成正比
and throwing more processors at the problem
但投入过多的处理器
is not going to help me very much,
并不能带来很大的帮助
OK? So let's just look at this
懂吗？看一下这个
just to get a sense of what's going on here.
感觉一下 这到底是怎么回事
Let's imagine that the constants are irrelevant,
让我们设想一下 常数的大小不是很重要
and we have, say, thousand by thousand matrices,
比如有1000乘以1000大小的矩阵
OK, so in that case,
在这种情况下
our parallelism is 1,000^3 divided by log of 1,000^2.
并行度就是1000^3/(log 1000)^2
What's log of 1,000? Ten, approximately,
log 1000是多少？近似等于10
right? Log base two of 1,000 is about ten,
以2为底的log 1000大概是10
so that's 10^2. So, you have about 10^7 parallelism.
所以这是10^2 所以并行度大概是10^7
How big is 10^7?
10^7是多大？
Ten million processors.
一千万个处理器
OK, so who knows of a machine with ten million processors?
谁知道有什么机器有一千万个处理器吗？
What's the most number of processors anybody knows about?
你们所知道的最多处理器有多少？
Yeah, not quite,
好吧 差不多
the IBM Blue Jean has a humungous number of processors,
IBM的“蓝色牛仔裤”有超多处理器
exceeding 10,000. Yeah.
超过一万个
Those were one bit processors.
但那是一位处理器
OK, so this is actually a pretty big number,
所以这实际上是非常大的数
and so, our parallelism is much bigger than a typical,
因此并行度也远远大于
actual number of processors.
典型、实际的处理器数量
So, we would expect to be able to
所以 我们就能期望
run this and get very good performance,
并行能起效 而且效果不错
OK, because we're never going to be
因为我们从来不会
limited in this algorithm by performance.
因为算法的限制而降低性能
However, there are some tricks we can do.
然而 确实有一些技巧能提升性能
One of the things in this code is that
其中一个是 在这段代码里
we actually have some overhead
实际上有一些开销
that's not apparent
没有表示出来
because I haven't run this code with you,
因为没有实际运行给你们看
although I could,
虽然可以跑一下
which is that we have this temporary matrix, T,
那就是这个临时矩阵T
and if you look at the execution stack,
如果查看程序的执行堆栈
we're always allocating T and getting rid of it, etc.
我们总是在分配T 然后又释放掉
And, one of the things
我要说的是
when you actually look at the performance of real code,
当你实际查看真实代码的性能时
which is now that you have your algorithmic background,
就像现在 你有一定算法知识背景
you're ready to go and do that with some insight.
当你准备好去做一个彻底的调查时
Of course, you're interested in
当然 你关心的
getting more than just asymptotic behavior.
将不仅仅是算法的渐近界限
You're interested in
你更关心的是
getting real performance behavior on real things.
得到实际的性能参数的信息
So, you do care about constants in that nature.
那么 你就会自然地关注一些常量
OK, and one of the things
你可能会发现
is having a large, temporary variable.
如果有一个大型临时变量
That turns out to be a lot of overhead.
它实际上会花费很多开销
And, in fact, it's often the case
而实际上 有种很常见情形是——
when you're looking at real code that
当你看到现实中的代码
if you can optimize for space,
如果你能优化存储空间
you also optimized for time.
那你同时也能优化时间
If you can run your code with smaller space,
如果你的代码占用更少的空间
you can actually run it with smaller time,
实际上 它也会花费更少的时间
tends to be a constant factor advantage.
大致有一个常量级的优势
But, those constants can add up,
但这些常量优势是可叠加的
and can make a difference in
并造成较大影响
whether somebody else's code is faster
最终决定 是别人的代码更快
or your code is faster,
还是你的更快
once you have your basic algorithm.
如果你们的基本算法都是一样的话
So, the idea is to, in this case,
所以在这种情况下 思路就是
we're going to get rid of it by trading parallelism
通过并行化 来去除隐藏开销
because we've got
因为我们有
oodles of parallelism here for space efficiency.
很多的并行运算来提高空间效率
OK, and the idea is we're going to get rid of T.
好的 我们的目的是去除T
OK, so let's throw this up.
好的 乾坤大挪移
So, who can suggest how I might get rid of T here,
谁知道是在这里如何去掉T的？
get rid of this temporary matrix?
怎么甩掉这个临时矩阵？
Yeah?
啥?
So, if you just did adding it into C?
如果只是把它加到C里
So, the issue that you get there
但问题是 如果这样做
if they're both adding into C
如果大家都加到C里
is you get interference between the two subcomputations.
那两个子运算之间会产生干扰
Now, there are ways of doing that that work out,
现在 有很多方法都是可行的
but you now have to worry about
但你必须考虑一下
things we're not going to talk about
一些我们不会细说的问题
such as mutual exclusion
比如互斥之类的
to make sure that as you're updating it,
来保证比如当你做更新时
somebody else isn't updating it,
其他人是更新不了的
and you don't have race conditions.
不会出现竞争的情况
But you can actually do it
但实际上你可以这样做
in this context with no race conditions.
因为这里没有竞争的情况
Yeah, exactly. Exactly, OK, exactly.
对 没错 是这样的
So, the idea is spawn off four of them.
方法就是将其衍生成四步
OK, they all update their copy of C,
全部都更新原来的C
and then spawn off the other four that add their values in.
然后再衍生四个新的再把它们的值加起来
So, that is a piece of code we'll call mult add.
所以这部分代码又称为“乘加”
And, it's actually going to do C gets C plus A times B.
用来计算C=C+A*B
OK, so it's actually going to add it in.
所以最后要加进来
So, initially you'd have to zero out C,
一开始要把C归零
but we can do that with code very similar to
但这个的代码就跟之前
the addition code with order n^2 work,
θ(n^2)的加法代码很像
and order log n critical path.
还有θ(log n)关键路径的代码
So that's not going to be
所以这不是
a big part of what we have to deal with.
我们必须要重点应付的部分
OK, so here's the code. We basically, once again,
这是代码 再一次
do the base and partition
分析基础情况 以及划分部分
which I'm not going to write out the code for.
这些就不再详细地写出代码了
We spawn a mult add of C1-1, A1-1, B1-1, n over 2,
然后为(C_11, A_11, B_11, n/2)衍生一个乘加函数
and we do a few more of those down to the fourth one.
然后在做几步 直到第四步
And then we put in a sync. And then we do the other four --
然后做一步同步 然后再做另外四步——
——and then sync when we're done with that.
——最后完成时 再进行同步
OK, does everybody understand that code?
大家都理解这些代码吗?
See that it basically does the same calculation.
可以看出 基本上都在进行相同的计算
We actually don't need to call add anymore,
实际上 不需要再调用相加函数了
because we are doing that
因为我们已经把它
as part of the multiply because we're adding it in.
归为乘法的一部分了 因为它包括了相加运算
But we do have to initialize.
但必须要先初始化
OK, we do have to initialize the matrix in this case.
在这种情况下 要对矩阵进行初始化
OK, so there is another phase.
那么 这是另一个阶段
So, people understand the semantics of this code？
大家理解这段代码的语义吧？
So let's analyze it.
我们来分析一下
OK, so what's the work of multiply, add of n?
对于n的乘加的功是多少？
It's basically the same thing, right?
基本是一样的 对不对？
It's order n^3 because the serial code
是θ(n^3) 因为这里的串行代码
is almost the same as the serial code up there,
几乎与上面的串行代码是一模一样的
OK, not quite,
虽然不全等
OK, but you get essentially the same recurrence
但基本是相同的递归
except you don't even have the add.
除了没有相加函数
You just get the same recurrence
得到的是相同的递归
but with order one here, oops, order one up here.
但这里有θ(1) 噢不对 θ(1)是在上面
So, it's still got the order n^3 solution.
所以 还是同样的解θ(n^3)
OK, so that, I think, is not too hard.
好的 我想这并不难理解
OK, so the critical path length, so there,
至于关键路径长度
let's write out, so multiply add of n,
写在这里  所以n的乘加运算
OK, what's my recurrence for this code?
这段代码的递归式是什么？
Yeah, 2M infinity, n over 2 almost that,
没错 2MA_∞(n/2) 差不多了
so order one. Plus order one, yeah.
还有θ(1) 加上θ(1)
OK, so the point is that
所以重点是
we're going to have, for the critical path,
对于关键路径 我们有
we're going to spawn these four off,
我们衍生出这四步
and so I take the maximum of whatever those is,
取其中最大值 无论这些是多少
which since they're symmetric is any one of them,
因为其中任意一个都是对称的
OK, and then I have to wait.
然后我需要等它做完
And then I do it again.
然后再做一次
So, that sync, once again,
所以这里的同步 再一次
translates into, in the analysis,
在分析中 我们可以看做是
it translates into a plus of the critical path,
关键路径的相加
which are the things I spawn off in parallel,
也等同于在并行衍生中
I do the max. OK, so people see that?
取最大值的操作 大家明白了没?
So, I get this recurrence,
所以得到这个递归
2MA of n over 2 plus order one,
2MA_∞(n/2)+θ(1)
and what's the solution to that?
它的解是多少？
OK, that's order n,
等于θ(n)
OK, because n to the log base two of two is n,
因为n的log 2(以2为底)次幂等于n
and that's bigger than one so we get order n.
它比1大 所以是θ(n)
OK, so the parallelism, we have p bar
那么 并行度P帽
is equal to MA one of n over MA infinity of n is equal to,
等于MA_1(n)/MA_∞(n)
in this case, n^3 over n, or order n^2.
在这个情况下 n^3/n 即θ(n^2)
OK, so for 1,000 by 1,000 matrices, for example,
举个例子 对于1000乘1000的矩阵
by the way, 1,000 by 1,000 is considered a small matrix these days,
顺便说一下 现在1000乘1000被认为只是一个小矩阵
because that's only one million entries.
因为只有100万个元
You can put that on your laptop no sweat.
你可以毫无压力地放到你的笔记本里
OK, so, but for 1,000 by 1,000 matrices,
但对于1000乘1000矩阵
our parallelism is about 10^6.
并行度大概是10^6
OK, so once again,
所以再一次
ample parallelism for anything we would run it on today.
在现在 并行度都足够让我们跑程序的
And as it turns out, it's faster in practice——
而实际应用中 它的运行效率更快
——because we have less space.
——因为使用了较少的空间
OK, so here's a game where,
所以这就是博弈
so, often the game you'll see in theory papers
你会经常在学术论文中见到博弈论
if you look at research papers,
如果你查阅研究论文 你会发现
people are often striving to get the most parallelism,
人们经常努力去争取最大的并行度
and that's a good game to play,
这是一个不错的博弈
OK, but it's not necessarily the only game.
但不是必要的唯一博弈
Particularly, if you have a lot of parallelism,
特别是 当你有很大的并行度时
one of the things that's very easy to do
你还可以很容易地做一件事
is to retreat on the parallelism
就是放弃一部分并行度
and gain other aspects that you may want in your code.
从而让你的代码去获得其他方面的性能
OK, and so this is a good example of that.
这就是一个很好的例子
In fact, and this is an exercise,
事实上 这是课后的练习
you can actually achieve work n^3,
你其实能取得n^3的功
order n^3 work, and a critical path of log n,
θ(n^3)的功 还有log n的关键路径
so even better than either of these two algorithms
所以说 甚至比之前那两个算法更好
in terms of parallelism.
从并行度来看的话
OK, so that gives you n^3 over log n parallelism.
所以 它给出了n^3/log n的并行度
So, that's an exercise.
这是课后习题
And then, the other exercise that I mention that
然后 我还提到了另一个不错的课后练习
that's good to do is parallel Strassen,
就是把施特拉森算法并行化
OK, doing the same thing with Strassen,
用施特拉森算法进行同样的编程
and analyze, what's the working critical path
然后分析 施特拉森代码的关键路径
and parallelism of the Strassen code?
还有并行度是多少？
OK, any questions about matrix multiplication?
对于矩阵乘法有什么疑问吗？
Yeah?
说吧？
Yeah, so that would take,
对了 它就会给...
that would add a log n to the critical path,
给关键路径加上一个log n
which is nothing compared to the n.
和n相比就不算什么了
Excuse me?
听不清
Well, you got to make sure C is zero to begin with.
要先保证C一开始归零
OK, so you have to set all the entries to zero,
即必须把所有元设为0
and so that will take you n^2 work,
这样才能给你n^2的功
which is nothing compared to
和这里的n^3的功相比
the n^3 work you're doing here,
又不算什么了
and it will cost you log n additional to the critical path,
它在关键路径上有额外的log n的开销
which is nothing compared to
和所之前的θ(n)相比
the order n that you're spending.
又不算什么了
Any other questions about matrix multiplication?
对于矩阵乘法还有其它问题吗？
OK, as I say, this all goes back to week two,
我都说了 这些都是第二周的内容
or something, in the class.
课堂上讲过的内容
Did you have a comment? Yes, you can.
听说你想发表意见？ 是的 可以
OK, yes you can.
你可以这样
It's actually kind of interesting to look at that.
实际去研究下的话 你会发现这很有趣
Actually, we'll talk later.
其实等下我就会讲到
We'll write a research paper after the class is over,
我们会在课后写一篇研究论文
OK, because there's actually
因为实际上
some interesting open questions there.
这些是很有意思的开放性话题
OK, let's move on to something
我们继续介绍一些
that you thought you'd gotten rid of weeks ago,
你们认为在几周前就摆脱了的东西
and that would be the topic of sorting.
那就是排序的话题
Back to sorting. OK, so we want to parallel sort now, OK?
回到排序 我们想要实现并行排序
Hugely important problem.
这是非常重要的问题
So, let's take a look at, so if I think about algorithms
让我们看一下 如果我要选一种排序算法
for sorting that sound easy to parallelize,
最适合拿来并行化的话
which ones sound kind of easy to parallelize?
哪一种排序算法最适合并行化?
Quick sort, yeah,
快速排序
that's a good one. Yeah, quick sort is
很好的一种排序算法 快速排序
a pretty good one to parallelize and analyze.
非常适合拿来并行化和做分析
But remember, quick sort has a little bit
但要记得 快速排序相比其它排序法
more complicated analysis than some other sorts.
分析起来会比较复杂一点
What's another one that looks like
还有没有其他的算法
it should be pretty easy to parallelize?
会比较容易进行并行化？
Merge sort.
归并排序
When did we teach merge sort? Day one.
什么时候学的归并排序？第一天
OK, so do merge sort
好 那就归并排序
because it's just a little bit easier to analyze.
因为它更容易分析
OK, we could do the same thing for quick sort.
用快速排序同样也可以
Here's merge sort,
这里是归并排序
OK, and it's going to sort A of p to r.
为A[p…r]排序
So, if p is less than r,
如果p小于r
then we get the middle element,
则取中间的元素
and then we'll spawn off since we have to, as you recall,
然后进行衍生 因为我们要... 好好回想下吧
when you merge sort you first recursively
当进行归并排序时 首先要递归地
sort the two sub-arrays.
为两个子数组排序
There's no reason not to do those parallel.
所以没理由不并行化
Let's just do them in parallel.
并行地跑下来
Let's spawn off, merge sort of (A,p,q),
衍生出(A,p,q)的归并排序
and spawn off, then, merge sort of (A,q+1,r),
还有然后衍生出来的(A,q+1,r)
And then, we wait for them to be done.
然后等这它们运算完
Don't forget your syncs.
别忘了同步
Sync or swim.
穷路同步 从不同富
OK, and then what to do what we are done with this?
然后在完成这些之后做什么？
OK, we merge.
是的 归并
OK, so we merge of A, p, q, r,
归并(A,p,q,r)
which is merge A of p up to q with A of q plus one up to r.
也就是归并A(p…q)与A(q+1…r)
And, once we've merged, we're done.
一旦归并结束 排序就完成了
OK, so this is the same code as we saw before in day one
这跟之前第一天看的代码是一样的
except we've got a couple of spawns in the sync.
除了这同步里多了几步衍生运算
So let's analyze this. So, the work is called T_1 of n,
分析一下 这里T_1(n)表示功
what's the recurrence for this?
这个的递归式是什么？
This really is going back to day one, right?
这真的在第一天讲过 是吧？
We actually did this on day one.
实际上在第一天做过这分析
OK, so what's the recurrence?
递归式是什么？
2T_1 of n over 2 plus order n
是2T_1(n/2)+θ(n)
merges order n time operation, OK?
归并花费θ(n)时间的操作
And so, that gives us a solution of n log n,
得出一个解是θ(n log n)
OK, even if you didn't know the solution,
即使你不知道怎么解的
you should know the answer,
也应该知道这答案
OK, which is the same as the serial code,
和串行代码的结论是一样的
not surprisingly. That's what we want.
不奇怪 这正是想要的
OK, critical path length, T infinity of n is equal to,
关键路径长度 T_∞(n)等于
OK, T infinity of n over 2 plus order n again.
好 T_∞(n/2)又是加上θ(n)
And that's equal to order n, OK?
这等于θ(n)
So, the parallelism is
所以并行度是
then p bar equals T_1 of n over T infinity of n
P帽等于T_1(n)/T_∞(n)
is equal to theta of log n.
等于θ(log n)
Is that a lot of parallelism?
这并行度是不是很多？
No, we have a technical name for that. We call it puny.
不是 有一个专业点的叫法 称之为“微小”
OK, that's puny parallelism. Log n?
这是“微小”的并行度 log n
Now, so this is actually probably a decent algorithm
这实际上可能是一个相当好的算法
for some of the small scale processors,
对于一些小规模的处理器来说
especially the multicore processors
尤其是多核处理器
that are coming on the market,
从市场上能买到的
and some of the smaller SMP, symmetric multiprocessors,
还有对于一些SMP：对称多处理器
that are available.
都是有用的
You know, they have four or eight processors or something.
它们有四个或八个处理器
It might be OK. There's not a lot of parallelism.
这算法可能可行 并行度不是很多
For a million elements, log n is about 20.
对于百万个元 log n大概是20
OK, and so and then there's constant overheads,etc.
因为还有一些常数阶的开销
This is not very much parallelism at all.
所以这个不是相当并行化
Question?
有问题吗？
Yeah, so how can we do better? I mean, it's like,
如何才能做得更好？我是说 就像是
man, at merge, right, it takes order n.
归并算法那样 花费θ(n)
if I want to do better, what should I do?
如果想要更好的性能 应该怎么做？
Yeah? Sort in-place,
说？原位排序
but for example if you do quick sort and partition,
例如你用快速排序 要划分数组
you still have a linear time partition.
你仍要用线性时间来做划分
So you're going to be very much in the same situation.
所以情况还是一样的
But what can I do here? Parallel merge.
但这里能怎么做？并行归并
OK, let's make merge go in parallel.
然我们并行地进行归并
That's where all the critical path is.
那是关系到关键路径的部分
Let's figure out a way of building a merge program
我们试着写一个新的归并程序
that has a very short critical path.
并令其有一条超短的关键路径
You have to parallelize the merge. This is great.
必须将归并操作并行化 非常好
It's so nice to see at the end of a course like this
我表示相当感动 像这样的课程 学到最后
that people have the intuition for,
你们能拥有一种直觉
oh, you can look at it and sort of see,
通过表面看透其本质
where should you put in your work?
知道哪里才是关键所在
OK, the one thing about algorithms is
关于算法的认识之一是
it doesn't stop you from
它不会在你编程时
having to engineer a program when you code it.
妨碍你设计一个程序
There's a lot more to coding a program well
编程要编得好 有很多工作要做
than just having the algorithm
而不仅仅是算法
as we talked about, also, in day one.
就像我们在第一天说的那样
There's things like making it modular,
还有一些工作比如 模块化
and making it maintainable,
使其具有可维护性
and a whole bunch of things like that.
还有诸如此类的一大堆事
But one of the things
但有一件事就是
that algorithms does is it tells you,
算法会告诉你
where should you focus your work.
哪里才是你要关注的地方
OK, there's no point in,
好吧 就不会是在...
for example, sort of saying,
比如说 就像是
OK, let me spawn off
我这里衍生出
four of these things of size n over 4
四个大小为n/4的运算
in hopes of getting, I mean, it's like,
我希望得到... 我是说像这些
that's not where you put the work.
这不是重点所在
You put the work in merge
需要把重点放在归并
because that's the one that's the bottleneck, OK?
因为这才是关键的瓶颈
And, that's the nice thing about algorithms is
这也是算法的精秒之处
it very quickly lets you hone in
让你迅速找到重点
on where you should put your effort,
让你有的放矢
when you're doing algorithmic design in engineering practice
让你在做算法设计的工程实践时更得心应手
So you must parallelize the merge.
你肯定要把归并并行化
The merge we're taking,
关注的是归并
so here's the basic idea we're going to use.
下面是我们的基本思路
So, in general, when we merge,
通常 当进行归并时
when we do our recursive merge,
当做递归合并时
we're going to have two arrays.
我们会用到两个数组
Let's call them A and B.
称之为A和B
I called them A there.
那边已经有一个A了
I probably shouldn't have used A.
可能不应该再用A来表示
I probably should have called them something else,
应该把它叫做其它的
but that's what my notes have,
但教案上就是这么写的
so we're going to stick to it.
还是继续用这个名字吧
But we get a little bit more space there
这里留多点空间
and see what's going on.
看看要怎么做
We have two arrays. I'll call them A and B,
有两个数组 称之为A和B
OK? And, what we're going to do,
我们打算做的是
these are going to be already sorted.
这些是已经排序好的
And our job is going to be to merge them together.
我们的工作是将它们归并到一起
So, what I'll do is I'll take the middle element of A.
要做的是取A中间那个元素
So this, let's say, goes from one to l,
这个假设是从1到l
and this goes from one to m.
这个是从1到m
OK, I'll take the middle element,
取中间的元素
the element at l over 2, say,
假设是l/2
and what I'll do is use binary search to figure out,
我们要做的是 用二分法检索来出
where does it go in the array B?
它在数组B中的位置
Where does this element go?
这个元素在哪？
It goes to some point here
在这里某个位置
where we have j here and j plus one here.
这里是j 还有这里是j+1
So, we know, since this is sorted,
因为数组已经排序好
that all these things are
所有这些元素
less than or equal to A of l over 2,
都小于或等于A[l/2]
and all these things are
还有所有这些元素
greater than or equal to A of l over 2.
都大于或等于A[l/2]
And similarly, since that element falls here,
同样的 因为这个元素在这里
all these are less than or equal to A of l over 2.
所有这些都小于或等于A[l/2]
And all these are going to be
还有所有这些都将
less greater than or equal to two.
大于或等于A[l/2]
OK, and so now what I can do is
现在我们能做的是
once I figured out where this goes,
一旦算出这个元素的位置
I can recursively merge this array with this one,
我就能递归地将这段数组和这段归并起来
and this one with this one,
还有这段和这段数组
and then if I can just concatenate them altogether,
然后就能够将它们连结到一起
I've got my merged array. OK, so let's write that code.
我就得到归并好的数组 写一下代码
Everybody get the gist of what's going on there,
每个同学都理解这个过程的主旨吗
how we're going to parallelize the merge?
它是如何进行并行化归并的？
Of course, you can see, it's going to get a little messy
当然你会觉得 这有一点混乱
because j could be anywhere.
因为j可能在任意地方
heres my code, parallel merge of,
这是代码 并行归并
and we're going to put it in C of one to n,
我们会把结果放进C[1…n]
so I'm going to have n elements.
所以有n个元素
So, this is doing merge A and B into C,
所以这个函数是将A和B归并到C
and n is equal to l plus m.
这里n=l+m
OK, so we're going to take two arrays
我们是将两个数组
and merge it into the third array, OK?
归并到第三个数组里
So, without loss of generality,
为了使其具有一般性
I'm going to say l is bigger than m as I show here
我要假设l大于m 正如这里表示的
because if it's not, what do I do?
因为如果不是这样 那该怎么做？
Just do it the other way around, right?
只要数组位置反过来做就行了 是吧
So, I figure out which one was bigger.
我要先搞清楚哪一个比较大
So that only cost me order one to test that or whatever.
那仅需要θ(1)的时间就能测出来
And then, I basically do a base case,
然后 分析基本情况
you know, if the two arrays are empty or whatever,
比如 如果两个数组是空的或是其它怎样
what you do in practice, of course, is, you know
当然 在实际工程中
if they're small enough, you just do a serial merge,
如果数组足够小 你只需要串行归并
OK, if they're small enough,
如果它们足够小的话
and I don't really expect to get much parallelism.
我也不期望能得到多大的并行度
There isn't much work there.
因为做的功不多
You might as well just do serial merge,
你也同样可以用串行归并实现
and be a little bit more efficient, OK?
可能还更有效率
So, do the base case.
好的 分析基本情况
So then, what I do is I find the j
然后所要做的是找出j
such that B of j is less than or equal to A of l over 2,
使得B[j]小于或等于A[l/2]
less than or equal to B of j plus one,
小于或等于B[j+1]
using binary search.
用二分法检索可得
What did recover binary search?
什么时候学的二分法检索？
Oh yeah, that was week one, right?
没错 第一周
That was first recitation or something.
好像是在第一堂复习课上
Yeah, it's amazing.
对 它非常神奇
OK, and now, what we do is
现在要做的是
we spawn off p merge of A of one, l over 2, B of one to j,
衍生出新的归并 A[1…l/2]与B[1…j]
and stick it into C of one, two, l over 2 plus j.
然后把结果归并到C[1…l/2+j]
OK, and similarly now, we can spawn off a merge of
然后同样地 衍生另一个归并
A of l over 2 plus one up to l. B of j plus one up to M,
A[l/2+1…l]与B[j+1…m]
and a C of l over two plus j plus one up to n.
归并到C[l/2+j+1…n]
And then, I sync.
然后进行同步
So, code is pretty straightforward,
代码非常直观
doing exactly what I said we were going to do over here,
也就是我刚刚在这演示的内容
analysis, a little messier, a little messier.
它的分析 呀咩 会有一点点混乱喔
So, let's just try to understand it
那在进行分析前
before we do the analysis.
我们先尝试理解一下
Why is it that I want to pick
为什么我要选择
the middle of the big array rather than the small array?
大数组里的中位元素 而不是小数组里面的？
What sort of my rationale there?
给个奶油我？
That's actually a key part,
这实际上是关键部分
going to be a key part of the analysis. Yeah?
是分析过程的关键部分 啊哈？
Yeah, imagine that B, for example,
对了 就例如 设想数组B
had only one element in it, or just a few elements,
它里面只有一个元素 或者只有极少量元素
then finding it in A might mean
那B的中位元素在A中的位置
finding it right near the beginning of A.
就很可能靠近A的开头部分
And now, I'd be left with subproblems that were very big,
这就会使得之后的子数组变得非常大
whereas here, as you're pointing out,
相对于这里 正如你所说的
if I start here, if my total number of elements is n,
如果从这里开始 元素的总数是n
what's the smallest that one of these recursions could be?
那这里递归出的数组长度最小是多少？
N over 4 is the smallest it could be,
最小可能是n/4
because I would have at least a quarter of the total
因为它至少是总元素的四分之一
number of elements to the left here or to the right here
无论是A的左边也好 右边也好
If I do it the other way around, my recursion,
如果反过来 则之后递归出的数组的大小
I might get a recursion that was nearly as big as n,
可能跟n差不多大
and that's sort of, once again,
那就变成... 再一次
sort of like the difference
这之间的差别就像
when we were analyzing quick sort with
当我们分析快排时
whether we got a good partitioning element or not.
看看是否能得到一个不错的分割元素那样
The partitioning element is somewhere in the middle,
如果分割元素在中间位置附近
we're really good, but it's always at one end,
那结果就非常好 但如果总在一端上
it's no better than insertion sort.
那效率可能都没有插入排序好
You want to cut off at least a constant fraction
在使用分治法时 你总希望分割时
in your divided and conquered
能有一个固定的比例
in order to get the logarithmic behavior.
从而得到对数时间的复杂度
OK, so we'll see that in the analysis.
我们会在接下来的分析中看到
But the key thing here is that
但这里关键的因素是
when we are going to do the recursion,
当进行递归操作时
we're going to have at least n over 4 elements in
我们至少有四分之一的元素
whatever the smaller thing is.
在无论哪一个小数组里
OK, but let's start.
让我们开始..
It turns out the work is the hard part of this.
看来功的分析是这部分的难点
Let's start with critical path length.
那我们先从关键路径长度开始
OK, look at that, critical path length.
看一下关键路径长度
OK, so parallel merge, so infinity of n is going to be,
好的 在并行归并中 PM_∞(n)将会
at most, so if the smaller piece has at least a quarter,
小于等于 如果最小的部分至少是四分之一
what's the larger piece going to
那这两个递归数组中
be of these two things here?
大一点那个最大有多大？
So, we have two problems spawning off.
我们现又衍生了两个子问题
Now, we really have to do max
现在我们取的是最大值
because they're not symmetric.
因为它们不是对称的
Which one's going to be worse?
最大那个能有多大？
One could have, at most, three quarters of n.
它最多可能占了四分之三的元素
Woops, 3n, of 3n over 4 plus,
小于等于PM_∞(3n/4) 再加上
OK, so the worst of those two is going to be
所以 这两个递归数组的最大那个
three quarters of the elements plus, what?
会占了四分之三的元素 再加上多少？
Plus log n. What's the log n?
加上log n  这个log n是什么？
The binary search. OK, and that gives me a solution of,
二分法检索 这条式的解是
this ends up being n to the, what?
这个最后等于n的多少次幂？
n to the zero, right.
n的零次幂 没错
OK, it's n to the log base four thirds of one.
它是n的log1(以3/4为底)次幂
OK, it was the log of anything of one is zero.
无论底是多少 log 1都为0
So, it's n to the zero.
所以它是n的0次方
So that's just one compared with log n,
所以这是1和log n的比较
tack on, it's log squared n.
要附加log 所以是θ(log²n)
So, we have a critical path of log squared n.
所以关键路径为log²n
That's good news.
这是个好消息
Now, let's hope that
现在我们祈祷
we didn't blow up the work by a substantial amount.
求出来的功不会大到爆炸
OK, so the work is PM_1 of n is equal to, OK,
好的 功PM_1(n)等于
so we don't know what the split is.
因为我们不知道分割点在哪
So let's call it alpha. OK, so alpha n in one side,
所以设分割比例为α 所以一边就是α·n
and then the work on the other side
然后另一边的功就是
will be PM of one of one minus alpha n plus,
PM_1((1-α)·n) 然后再加上
and then still order of log n
还是二分法检索的θ(log n)
to the binary search where, as we've said,
这里正如我们说过的
alpha is going to fall
α将落在
between one quarter and three quarters.
1/4与3/4之间
OK, how do we solve a recurrence like this?
怎么解这样的一个递归式？
What's the technical name for this kind of recurrence?
这一类递归的专业叫法是什么？
Hairy. It's a hairy recurrence.
毛烦 毛烦递归
How do we solve hairy recurrences?
怎么解毛烦递归
Substitution. OK, good.
替换法 很好
Substitution. OK, so we're going to say
替换法 那么我们假设
PM one of k is less than or equal to,
PM_1(k)小于或等于
OK, I want to make a good guess here,
这里要来一个大胆的猜想
OK, because I've fooled around with it.
因为我已经被它搞好毛烦了
I want it to be linear,
我猜它是线性的
so it's going to have a linear term, a times k
那么它就有一个线性系数 a·k减去
minus and then I'm going to do b log k.
然后减去b·log k
So, this is this trick of subtracting a low order term.
这是减去一个低阶项的技巧
Remember that in substitution in order to make it stronger?
还记得吗？ 这样可以使得替换法更强大
If I just did ak it's not going to work
如果只有a·k 那是没有用的
because here I would get n,
因为这边求出来就是n
and then when I did this substitution
然后这边一替换
I'm going to get a alpha n,
就会得到一个a·α·n
and then a one minus alpha n, and those two together
后面这个就是a·(1-α)n 这两项加起来
are already going to add up to everything here.
就恰好是等号左边这一项
So, there's no way I'm going to get it bounded
因为后面还有一个θ(log n) 这样一来
when I add this term in.
式子就不成立了
So, I need to subtract something
所以我们要在这两项中
from both of these so as to absorb this term,
减去一部分来抵消掉这一项
OK? So, I'm skipping over those steps,
懂吗？ 我就跳过中间的步骤了
OK, because we did those steps in lecture two or something.
因为第二节课就已经讲过了类似的内容
OK, so that's the thing I'm going to guess
这就是要猜想的部分
where a and b are greater than zero.
这里a与b都大于0
OK, so let's do the substitution.
我们来代入一下
OK, so we have PM one of n is less than or equal to,
PM_1(n)小于或等于
OK, we substitute this inductive hypothesis in
好的 我们把这个归纳的假设
for these two guys.
代入到这两项中去
So, we get a alpha n minus b log of alpha n
得出一个a·(α*n)-b·log(α·n)
plus a of one minus alpha n
加上a·((1-α)n)
minus b log of one minus alpha,
减去b·log((1-α)n)
maybe another parentheses there,
这里还有一个括号
one minus alpha n,
(1-α)n
and even leave myself enough space here
虽然已经预留了很多位置了（但还是不够）
Plus, let me just move this over
加上...把这个写到这边
so I don't end up using too much space.
这样才不至于占用太多地方
So, b log of one minus alpha n
好的 b·log((1-α)n)
plus theta of log n. How's that?
加上θ(log n) 如何?
Are we OK on that? OK, so that's just substitution.
明白吗？这只是进行代入而已
Let's do a little algebra.
我们做一下代数运算
That's equal to a of times alpha na times one minus alpha n.
它等于把a乘以α·n 再乘以(1-α)n
That's just an, OK, minus,
那就等于a·n 再减去
well, the b isn't quite so simple.
b那项就没那么简单了
OK, so I have a b term.
取出系数b
Now I've got a whole bunch of stuff there.
现在后面有一大堆的式子
I've got log of alpha n.
我有log(α·n)
I have, then, this log of one minus alpha n,
然后是这个log((1-α)n)
OK, one minus alpha n, and then plus theta log n.
(1-α)n 然后加上θ(log n)
Did I do that right? Does that look OK?
做得对不对？看起来没错吧？
OK, so look at that.
接下来要看
OK, so now let's just multiply some of this stuff out.
现在把一些参数乘出来
So, I have an minus b times,
得出a·n减去b乘以
well, log of alpha n is just log alpha plus log n.
log(α·n)等于logα加上log n
And then I have plus log of one minus alpha plus log n,
然后加上log(1-α)加上log n 最后加上θ(log n)
OK, plus theta log n. That's just more algebra,
加上θ(logn) 这变得更代数化了
OK, using our rules for logs.
用的是log的运算法则
Now let me express this
我把它比作是
as my solution minus my desired solution minus a residual,
实际的解减去预期的解再减去一个残差
an minus b log n, OK, minus, OK,
a·n减去b·log n 减去
and so that was one of these b log n's, right, is here.
这个是这些b·log n中的一个 这一个
And the other one's going to end up in here.
还有其它的最后会在这里
I have B times log n plus log of alpha
b·log n加上
times one minus alpha minus, oops, I've got too many.
log(α(1-α))减去 哎呀 写得太复杂了
Do I have the right number of closes.
右括号的数量没错吧
Close that, close that, that's good,
闭合那个 闭合那个 没错
minus theta log n. Two there.
减去θ(log n) 这里两个右括号
Boy, my writing is degrading. OK, did I do that right?
我的板书真是有失身份 写得对不对？
Do I have the parentheses right?
括号都没错吧？
That matches, that matches,
对应这个 对应这个
that matches, good.
全部对应 很好
And then B goes to that, OK, good.
然后b在那里 没错 很好
OK, and I claim that is less than or equal to
我宣称这个小于或等于
an minus B log n if we choose B large enough.
a·n-b·logn  如果选择的b足够大的话
OK, this mess dominates this
这团乱糟糟的要大于这个
because this is basically a log n here,
因为这个基本上是一个log n
and this is essentially a constant.
还有这个本质上是一个常量
OK, so if I increase B,
如果增大b
OK, times log n, I can overcome that log n,
乘以log n 能够远大于这个θ(log n)
whatever the constant is,
无论这个被渐近符隐藏的
hidden by the asymptotic notation,
常数因子有多大
OK, such that B times log n plus log of alpha
这样b·log n加上
times one minus alpha dominates the theta log n.
log(α(1-α))大于θ(log n)
OK, and I can also choose
而且我还可以选择
my base condition to be big enough
基础的条件 使其大到足以
to handle the initial conditions,
应付初始条件
whatever they might be.
不管条件是什么
OK, so we'll choose A big enough --
选择a 让它大到足以——
——to satisfy the base of the induction.
——满足归纳的基本情形
OK, so thus PM_1 of n is equal to theta n, OK?
因此PM_1(n)等于θ(n)
So I actually showed O, and it turns out,
虽然我只证明了O(n) 但实际上
the lower bound that it is omega n is more straightforward
下限Ω(n)的证明会更直观一点
because the recurrence is easier
因为递归会容易一些
because I can do the same substitution.
因为我可以做同样的替换
I just don't have to subtract off low order terms.
只是不需要减去低阶的那一项
OK, so it's actually theta, not just O.
所以实际上用的是θ 而不是O
OK, so that gives us a log,
所以这给出……
what did we say the critical path was?
我们说关键路径是多少？
The critical path is log squared n for the parallel merge.
并行归并的关键路径是log²n
So, let's do the analysis of merge sort using this.
那就用这个来做归并排序的分析
So, the work is, as we know already,
所以 做的功是 我们都知道了
T_1 of n is theta of n log n
T_1(n)=θ(n log n)
because our work that we just analyzed was order n,
因为刚才分析过功是θ(n)
same as for the serial algorithm, OK?
与串行算法相同
The critical path length, now,
而关键路径是
is T infinity of n is equal to,
T_∞(n)等于
OK, so in normal merge sort,
在一般的归并排序里
we have a problem of half the size, T of n over 2 plus,
取数组大小的一半 T(n/2) 加上
now, my critical path for merging
现在 归并的关键路径
is not order n as it was before.
不再是之前的θ(n)
Instead, it's just over there.
取代它的就在这里
Log squared n, there we go.
θ(log²n） 就是它
OK, and so that gives us theta of log cubed n.
所以得出θ(log³n）
So, our parallelism is then theta of n over log cubed n.
所以并行度是θ(n/log³n）
And, in fact, the best that's been done is,
实际上 已知最好的
sorry, log squared n, you're right.
不好意思 是log²n 你是对的
Log squared n because it's n log n over log cubed n.
log²n  因为它是n(log n)/log³n
It's n over log squared n, OK?
这个是n/log²n
And the best, so now I wonder if I have a typo here.
所以最好的是 我不确信这里教案是不是打错了
I have that the best is,
已有的最好并行度是
p bar is theta of n over log n. Is that right?
p帽等于θ(n/log n）没错吧？
I think so. Yeah, that's the best to date.
是这样的 对 那是目前最好的
That's the best to date. By Occoli, I believe,
是目前最有效的 应该是由Occoli发明的
is who did this, for this
是他增加了你们的期末考题
So you can actually get a fairly good, but it turns out
所以最终能够得到一个相当不错的并行度
sorting is a really tough problem to parallelize
但事实上 你很难给排序并行化
to get really good constants where you want to make it
因为你很难凑到一些很好的参数
so that it's running exactly the same.
让每个并行部分都一致
Matrix multiplication,
而矩阵相乘
you can make it run in parallel and get
你可以让它并行运行 并得到
straight, hard rail, linear speed up with a number of processors
直观 坚实的方法 让它随着处理器的数量线性加速
There is plenty of parallelism,
它有很大量的并行度
and running on more processors,
可以在更多的处理器上运行
every processor carries a full weight. With sorting,
每个处理器都满负载 但对于排序
typically you lose, I don't know,
你一般会丧失... 具体不清楚
20% in my experience, in terms of other stuff going on
我的经验大概是20%的并行度 还要顾及别的问题
because you have to work really hard
因为你必须花很多功夫
to get the constants of this merge algorithm down
才能使归这种归并算法的常量阶
to the constants of that normal merge, right?
小于普通归并的常量阶
I mean that's a pretty good algorithm, right,
我说这 是一个非常不错的算法
the one that just goes, BUZZING SOUND,
它跑起来嘚嘞嘚嘞嘚嘞的
and just takes two lists and merges them like that.
取两个链表然后 像这样归并到一起
So, it's an interesting issue.
这是一个很有意思的问题
And a lot of people work very hard on sorting,
很多人在排序上努力钻研
because it's a hugely important problem,
因为它是一个非常重要的问题
and how it is that you can actually get the constants down
要如何让常量阶变小
while still guaranteeing that
同时仍然保证
it will scale up with a number of processors.
它能按处理器的数量成比例递减
OK, that's our little sojourn into parallel land,
这只是并行苦海边的小贝壳
and next week we're going to talk about caching,
另外 下周我们讲介绍缓存
which is another very important area of algorithms,
那是另一个非常重要的算法领域
and of programming in general.
对于通常的编程也很重要